So syntax
of classes:
How do we represent classes
later in a class diagram?
I'm doing this here for an example
that we can then easily generalize to
other
situations.
Namely, the example
is to be:
A class of points
is to be created.
So we want to store
points of the two-dimensional space.
So we will have x and
y coordinates, and some operations on these
points.
So maybe this is supposed to be a vector
graphics domain again somehow, which we want to specify in
an object-oriented
way this time.
You could
imagine that.
Then there will be a graph at the
end, and in the graph there will be individual
nodes, each of which is such
a box (so a little graph).
And what will
appear in it?
That will be a
three-part box in each case.
And there's first of all a class
name, so the identification of the class itself.
Then there is an area
where attributes can be entered.
In this case, these are the information to
be stored, i.e. the x and y coordinates.
This is a
number in each case.
This is specified
here as type.
This is not always done
in such detail so early on.
So we saw examples earlier
where the type information was missing.
Usually, in the exercises (and later on in
the exam), we will expect you to put
meaningful type
information on there.
And then there is this
third area, where operations or
methods can be recorded
(also with their types).
This is of course somehow the bridge
to dynamic modeling, where you would then express
what these methods
are supposed to do.
Whereas here you just statically
state what their types are.
As
a comment:
Of course, there
are already activities here.
For example, one may move a point
in x- and y-direction to any number differences.
Nevertheless, what is written
here is still static modeling.
Because there is no code or
description of what the operations do.
There is only the
name and the types.
On the one hand the
argument types are interesting, which are
in
brackets.
So you can move a point, and then you
have to say by what you want to move it,
by
what differences.
And then there is no
return value for this operation.
Why
not?
Because this moving acts
directly on the point itself.
And there, when we introduced object
orientation, we had said that then no
explicit specification is needed, because implicitly
it operates on the concrete point.
On the other hand, if we wanted to determine, for
example, the vector length, that is, the length of the
vector from the coordinate origin to the current point,
then this would not be a change of the
point, but we
want to calculate something.
We don't need arguments because we are working
on the point itself and don't need any
other
information.
But we want to get a
number back instead of changing the point.
Then we would just
say here's what comes out.
And then this
is the result.
So the vector length returns a number, that's
why it says that as the result type here.
A couple
of other comments.
First of all, the attributes that are
here, these are not attributes of the class
per
se.
So of course they are in the
class diagram as attributes on the class.
But it's not that the class as
a whole has an x and y coordinate.
Rather, the class is a collection of
objects, namely individual points, and each instance has
attributes for these
x and y values.
So
it's important:
These are what
are called instance attributes.
They ultimately belong to
the instances of the class.
So to the objects that we'll form
later, and not to the class itself.
But they are kept in the class
because all objects of the class should have
an x and y value each
(but different values for different objects).
Here is simply the information that
these two values should always be present.
Then a detail you may know
if you have done object-oriented programming
before.
Or what you may also encounter
when you look at examples from books.
Sometimes there are some "funny symbols"
at the attributes or at the
methods, some special
symbols: Plus, minus.
Sometimes these can also
be designations, i.e. character strings.
But sometimes they are
just these short symbols.
These are so-called visibility
annotations on the attributes.
They say something about, later in
the implementation, from which other objects
instance attributes and
methods may be accessed.
We will
ignore that completely.
So that doesn't matter
to us in the modeling.
If you see something like that in
an example (it won't occur in our lecture
and exercise), if you see examples from
elsewhere, you can ignore those modifiers for
the purpose
of this lecture.
And then another way to pack
even more information into the class.
Even in giving this representation, what
we had done now was we gave
the
attributes types.
Sometimes you give
them default values.
Where the idea then is that if in
individual objects, for example, the x coordinate is not
explicitly assigned, then the default value
from the class specification would simply apply.
Then you would
write it like this:
So x must be an
integer, and the default is zero.
That would mean then that if in an object
of this class to the x nothing is said,
it would have simply
already directly the value zero.
Now, of course, classes
are there to describe objects.
So the goal is to describe with
a class the structure of certain objects.
And then, of course, an instance
of a class represents a concrete
object.
So our Point class can have
many objects, which are its manifestation.
And a concrete point, for example my concrete
point of the class "Point", would then be
specified by assigning concrete
numbers to the instance attributes.
You would then write
that down like that.
So you can certainly notate the class
and the object together, and then say
by this particular
kind of arrow:
This is an
instance of this class.
And then there are
only two sections here.
The name of the object and the indication
that it is an object of this class.
Then there's this syntax underline,
ultimately to distinguish classes and objects.
But most importantly, there is
no method box in the objects.
So this part down here
doesn't exist in the individual objects.
Why
not?
Because this
code is reused.
So while each object in the class may
have its own x and y values, the
functionality (moving a point, determining the
vector length of a point, etc.) is
not something that is
different for individual points.
So the functionality is
the same for all points.
That's why the methods/operations are native to
the class and not to individual instances
of
the class.
That's why there are
no methods on the right.
This is a typical mistake in
exercises/exams, that methods are also specified for
objects.
This should not be the case
and can lead to a point deduction.
So if you want to have different behavior
for different objects, then they would simply not
be objects of
the same class.
Then you would
have two different classes.
So there can still be classes
that also store two integers, for example
a class
for arithmetic fractions.
There you also
need two numbers.
But that would not be a point
class, because it would have completely different operations.
Then you would have
a second class for fractions.
Of it there
would be also objects.
They would also
store two integers each.
But in the different classes for points
and for fractions there would be different operations.
And the objects then don't have to
store any operations, because they each belong to
one class and that determines
which functionality is available for them.
Another hint
for the exercise:
There we will also have something like this,
that you should specify objects to classes or a
class.
Then you don't have to do that,
unless it is explicitly required, by copying
the class again and specifying the
objects and always making these instantiation
arrows.
It is then also sufficient (if the
class is clear) that you simply specify such
objects.
That would be the
relationship between classes and objects.
There are also relationships between
classes in the class diagram.
A first such relationship
is the so-called inheritance.
This is about the fact that classes can be
similar to each other, or a class can be in
a certain sense an
extension of another class.
An example for our
graphics domain would be:
We have points that store
certain information and offer certain
methods.
And then it may just be that
we have another concept, that of colored points.
What is
a colored point?
A colored point is still a point,
so it must also have coordinates x, y,
but should also have a
color (and perhaps other operations).
So we would have
to store a color.
And maybe there is an operation
that translates a colored point to grayscale.
This is an operation that makes no sense
on points in general, only on colored points.
That's why it
would be native here.
Just as color, of course, is
precisely the distinguishing feature of colored
points from normal points, and
that's why it's specified here.
What is written here on the right are
not substitutions for the things that are written here.
These are always
additional information/additional aspects.
So also the ColoredPoint
has an x- and y-coordinate.
They just don't have to be
specified here anymore because they are inherited.
This is exactly what this arrow
expresses, especially with this special kind of
arrowhead.
So ColoredPoint
inherits from Point.
That is, attributes of Point
are also attributes of ColoredPoint.
And there can be
more information here, more attributes.
Methods of Point are also methods
of ColoredPoint, but ColoredPoint can provide
even
more functionality.
This is called
superclass or superclass.
That would
be here:
The more general class would
be the superclass or superclass.
And the specialized concept of
ColoredPoint here, that's called subclass or
subclass.
Sometimes people
then ask here:
Is there
also multiple inheritance?
Can you inherit
from multiple things?
So could ColoredPoint also
inherit from two different classes?
How is it
with these arrows?
What is
possible there?
Are different classes allowed
to inherit from Point?
We'll talk about
that in a moment.
We could also ask
about our library example:
Is there also
somehow meaningful inheritance conceivable?
One must
always consider:
Are there aspects there
that could be generalized?
For example, where different
classes have something in common?
So let's assume that there are
other media than books in the library.
Then we could
introduce CDs, videos, magazines.
And we could come up
with a new class for each.
And then at some point we might
notice that these different media have certain
things
in common.
So while only the magazine has magazine numbers
and maybe only the videos have a playing time,
one author and one title is
what all of these media have.
So maybe it would make sense
to introduce a class for media in
general and then inherit specialized
classes for books, CDs, etc.
That's then part of the
design, also finding meaningful such relationships.
I had
already said that:
The subclass inherits attributes and
methods (and later other relationships we
will discuss) of the
superclass, and can add more.
One aspect for implementation that is
not so important now for static modeling
is that methods of
the superclass can be overridden.
I had
said that here:
All methods that exist for
Point also exist for ColoredPoint.
But it could be that the behavior of
some of these methods must be slightly different
for
ColoredPoints.
So then you would not change that
the methods exist, but what they do.
And for the new methods, of course, you have
to say what they do anyway, because the Point itself
doesn't know anything
about gray coloring.
And another important point of this kind of
relationship, inheritance, is that this is to be understood
in such a way that any object of the
subclass can also be considered an object of the
superclass.
That's where we
talk about polymorphism/polymorphism.
In the sense that everything you can
do with Points, you can still do
with
ColoredPoint.
So ColoredPoints is not just some other thing
that happens to also have an x and
y
coordinate.
But ColoredPoint is really to be seen
as also a point, but still additional information
to
it.
Everything that goes with points
must also go with colored points.
Otherwise it would be
wrong to have inheritance here.
So you shouldn't just connect arbitrary concepts
by inheritance just because they happen to have
similar
data stores.
It's really
always about that:
There has to be a real
generalization/specialization relationship between the two classes.
Because then this can be
used in a meaningful way.
And while we're on
inheritance, there are a few
more structural
things to consider.
So soon we don't want
to have just two classes.
We're going to generalize
or enrich that, after all.
That we don't just have two classes and
their relationship, but then a whole class diagram
with several classes
and their relationships.
And then you can get into
situations where certain constellations no longer make
sense.
There you have
to consider some things.
Especially for the moment,
it's simply what's recorded here.
So it
says here:
"Constellations that
are forbidden."
What is forbidden would be
first of all any circularities.
So you can't
inherit in a circle.
It can't be that B inherits from A,
C inherits from B, and A inherits from C.
It could already be that B inherits
from A and C inherits from B.
So, if this arrow was gone
here, the situation would be okay.
But with all three arrows here, we would
have a situation that would not make sense.
So it just wouldn't be allowed at all
to specify this class diagram with such a circular
inheritance
chain.
Finally, for similar reasons,
self-inheritance is also not useful.
So a class
cannot inherit from itself.
Nor can a class inherit twice,
so to speak, from another class.
In all these cases, of course,
the direction of the arrows is relevant.
Not here, so
here it wouldn't matter.
If the arrow were the other
way around, it would still be forbidden.
In the other situations the
picture could change in each case.
Whereas here, if the arrow were
reversed, it would be circular again.
Would be forbidden so to speak for another
reason and not because of this double inheritance.
And if you were to turn an arrow
around here, you would no longer have circularity.
So circularity really means: in the
direction of the arrows, a circle.
If you were to turn the arrow around here,
you would no longer have circularity, because you could
not go in a
circle following the arrows.
But then you would
have a double inheritance.
Then C would inherit
from A and from B.
This is allowed in principle in UML,
but not all programming languages support it.
We will pay special attention to
whether this should be allowed or not.